Kurt Taylor

Address: 70 Richmond Road, Bristol BS6 5EW
Telephone Number: +447425608190
Email Address: kurt.taylor@bristol.ac.uk
Date of Birth: July 16th, 1994

Profile

A motivated, adaptable individual with well-honed communication skills from a diversified set of experiences. Strong track record in science education with an in-depth understanding of epidemiology. A love for writing and exceptional organisation and management capabilities. An intense curiosity and thirst for intellectual stimulation. Experience in leading large international scientific collaborations. I am in the final year of a 4-year PhD studentship seeking opportunities and experiences that could lead to a successful career in scientific research.

Education

- 2017-2021 Doctor of Philosophy (PhD), Integrative Cardiovascular Science (Epidemiology); University of Bristol, UK
 - o Thesis title: The epidemiology of congenital heart disease: identifying causal maternal risk factors.
 - o Fully funded studentship via the British Heart Foundation.
 - Year 1 is an interdisciplinary training year with years 2-4 focusing on my main PhD research.
 - I have gained experience in bioinformatic analysis, publishing in high-impact scientific journals, laboratory work, teaching, public speaking and presenting to a wide-range of audiences.
- 2014-2017 Bachelor of Science (BSc Hons), Sport and Exercise Science, First; University of Surrey, UK
 - Deep understanding of human biology, psychology and biomechanics developed through rigorous academic units as well as varied laboratory sessions

Employment and Experience

My employment to date has taught me how to work effectively on my own and also as part of a team; having been employed from a young age, my worth ethic has excelled, learning to use my initiative to complete tasks required of me.

- January 2019 Visiting researcher, University of Copenhagen, Section of Epidemiology, Denmark
 - Visiting researcher for 2 weeks undertaking analyses as part of a wider project.
- **2019/ongoing Teaching,** University of Bristol, UK
 - After completing the 'starting to teach' training course, I was enrolled as a teacher on the Bristol Medical School short course: Introduction to epidemiology.
- 2019/ongoing Freelance medical writer, Aspire Scientific, UK
 - As a freelance medical writer, I help produce a diverse range of high-quality scientific materials predominantly in the form of scientific manuscripts. This role often has strict deadlines.
- 2018/ongoing Club captain, Bristol and West AC, UK
 - Being the men's club captain for my running club is a rewarding task and helps me make use of my exceptional organisational skills.
- 2019 Events organisation, MRC Integrative Epidemiology Unit, UK
 - I was part of the organisation committee for the 2019 International Mendelian Randomization conference.
- May 2016-August 2016 Summer internship as a clinical exercise scientist, Surrey Human Performance Institute, UK
 - A patient-facing position located within a lab at Surrey Sports Park, as well as carrying out Cardiopulmonary Exercise Testing at Ashford and St Peter's Hospital.
- August 2013-January 2015 Sales advisor, Vodafone UK
- December 2010 August 2013 Fire protection engineer, Pipetek services Ltd and Bryland Fire Ltd.

Kurt Taylor

Publications and research

I am an advocate of open science and the publication of pre-specified analysis plans to improve reproducibility and prevent publication bias. A list of my active and ongoing projects can be found here: https://osf.io/82vq6/.

Published research

- Taylor K, McBride N, J Goulding N et al. Metabolomics datasets in the Born in Bradford cohort [version 1; peer review: awaiting peer review]. Wellcome Open Res 2020, 5:264
 (https://doi.org/10.12688/wellcomeopenres.16341.1)
- 2. **Taylor K**, Thomas R, Mumme M *et al*. Ascertaining and classifying cases of congenital anomalies in the ALSPAC birth cohort [version 1; peer review: awaiting peer review]. *Wellcome Open Res* 2020, **5**:231 (https://doi.org/10.12688/wellcomeopenres.16339.1)
- 3. **Taylor, K**.; L. Santos Ferreira, D.; West, J.; Yang, T.; Caputo, M.; A. Lawlor, D. Differences in Pregnancy Metabolic Profiles and Their Determinants between White European and South Asian Women: Findings from the Born in Bradford Cohort. *Metabolites 9, 190* (2019). http://dx.doi.org/10.3390/metabo9090190
- 4. **Taylor, K.**, Davey Smith, G., Relton, C.L. *et al.* Prioritizing putative influential genes in cardiovascular disease susceptibility by applying tissue-specific Mendelian randomization. *Genome Med* 11, 6 (2019). https://doi.org/10.1186/s13073-019-0613-2

Pre-prints

- 1. **Taylor K**, Elhakeem A, Nader JLT, Yang T, Isaevska E, Richiardi L, et al. The effect of maternal pre-/early-pregnancy BMI and pregnancy smoking and alcohol on congenital heart diseases: a parental negative control study. *medRxiv*; 2020 Sep. https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.09.29.20203786
- 2. Richardson TG, Mykkanen J, Pahkala K, Ala-Korpela M, Bell JA, **Taylor K**, et al. Evaluating the direct effects of childhood adiposity on adult systemic metabolism: A multivariable Mendelian randomization analysis. medRxiv; 2020 Aug. https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.08.25.20181412

Presentations, talks and public speaking

Oral presentations

- June 2020 Society for Epidemiologic Research 2020, Boston, USA
 - Invited for oral presentation (meeting cancelled due to COVID-19 pandemic) Using an untargeted metabolomics platform to explore associations between maternal metabolites and congenital heart disease in the offspring.
- 4th October 2019 University of Surrey, Surrey, UK
 - I was invited to give a one hour talk about my time at the University of Surrey and how I progressed to a successful PhD student. Audience consisted of ~50 new undergraduate students.
- 27th September 2019 Born in Bradford Science Festival, Bradford, UK
 - Sofa session lasting 1 hour 10 mins talking to a mixed audience including members of the public, researchers and policy makers about my research and what we use blood samples for in the Born in Bradford cohort

Poster presentations

- 22nd October 2019 DOHaD 2019, Melbourne, Australia
 - o Poster presentation Differences in Pregnancy Metabolic Profiles and Their Determinants between White European and South Asian Women: Findings from the Born in Bradford Cohort.

Kurt Taylor

Applied Qualifications, Training and Key Skills

Where possible, I attend educational courses which could benefit my research and personal development. I am always keen on learning and have previously studied free online courses. Some examples of the training and qualifications I have received to date are listed below.

Bristol Medical School short training courses

- Introduction to epidemiology (5 days)
- Introduction to statistics (5 days)
- Mendelian randomisation (3 days)
- Systematic reviews and meta-analysis (4 days)
- Causal inference in epidemiology (3 days)
- Genetic epidemiology (5 days)
- Register of exercise professionals' level 3 personal trainer
- Biostatical analysis of genotype data
- Data Skills Workshop, November 2019
 - Funded by Cancer Research UK. Involved an application process to be accepted onto the course.
 Main focus on reproducible research.
- Statistical packages
 - o R (proficient)
 - Stata (basic use)
 - Microsoft Office (proficient)
- Public engagement of science
 - o Public speaking at Born in Bradford Science Festival, September 2019
 - Cancer Research UK public engagement training workshop
 - Communicating my research through social media. Example: https://twitter.com/KurtSci1994/status/1174329499313475585?s=20

<u>Interests</u>

I have a real passion for endurance-based sports, adventure and understanding how the body physiologically reacts to these types of activity. Since the age of eleven, I have raised thousands of pounds for various charities; my proudest achievement was successfully climbing Mount Kilimanjaro for my local hospice; a truly amazing and challenging experience. I am a competitive distance runner, training 6 or 7 days a week and competing on a national level. My running has taken me to places such as the high Atlas Mountains in Morocco and quiet suburban villages in The Gambia.